Preliminary Inventory to the Oliver J. Caldwell Papers, 1937-1986
Hoover Institution Archives
Oliver J. Caldwell Papers,
1937-1986
78085
Caldwell, Oliver J. (Oliver Johnson), 1904-1990
13 manuscript boxes (5.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Speeches, writings, memoranda, reports, and correspondence, relating to international education, U.S. educational policy, conditions in China prior to World War II, and operations of the U.S. Office of Strategic Services in China during World War II.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
United States. Office of Education; United States. Office of Strategic Services; Education; Education--United States; International education; Secret service--United States; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--China; World War, 1939-1945--Secret service; China; China--Social conditions; United States--Politics and government; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Armed Forces
Container List
- "Bird of Heaven," memoir by Caldwell of his childhood in China. Typescript (Box 1.)
- A Secret War: Americans in China, 1944-1945, book by Caldwell. Printed copy
- Maps prepared for use in A Secret War
- Office of Strategic Services reports on operations and conditions in China, 1944-1945 (3 folders)
- "Pilgrimage to the Lotus," by Caldwell, ca. 1940, relating to Buddhist monasteries. Typescript
- "China, the Beautiful Country: An Introduction to China for Young Americans," by Caldwell, ca. 1960. Typescript (2 folders)
- Partial bibliography of writings by Caldwell, 1953-1970
- Report by Howland Sargeant on U.S. program for exchange of students and industrial trainees, 1946
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, 1953-1957
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, 1958-1959 (Box 2.)
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, 1960
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, 1961-1962 (Box 3.)
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, January-June 1963
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, July-December 1963
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, 1964 (Box 4.)
- Speeches and writings by Caldwell for U.S. Office of Education, 1965
- Statistics on international education, 1961
- "Problems and Solutions in International Education," by Caldwell, 1963. Mimeograph (2 folders)
- Papers relating to International Conference on Public Education, Geneva, 1965
- Chart of proposed organization of international education in U.S. Office of Education, 1965
- Plan for a polycultural college, 1963-1964
- Papers relating to The Bridge (later Center for Advanced Intercultural Studies), 1964-1973 (4 folders)
- "Education for Unity in Diversity," report of The Bridge, 1970 (Box 5.)
- Correspondence with White House officials regarding international education, 1970-1972
- Papers relating to Southern Illinois University International Services Division Planning Conference, 1966
- Background notes for the Conference on the International Dimensions of Southern Illinois University, 1966
- Reports by Caldwell for Southern Illinois University, 1967-1968
- Speech by Caldwell to African Student Association, Southern Illinois University, 1968
- Papers relating to Southern Illinois University, 1968
- Writings by Caldwell for Southern Illinois University, 1967-1971
- Writings by Caldwell for the Commission on the International Dimensions of Southern Illinois University (Box 6.)
- Papers relating mostly to Southern Illinois University, 1966-1975 (3 folders and loose material)
- "The Merchants of Light," study by Caldwell on international education, 1971. Typescript
- University of Miami proposal prepared by Caldwell (Box 7.)
- "How the Student Ships Were Launched (How to Succeed by Doing Everything Wrong," memoir by Caldwell, 1977. Typescript
- Speeches by Caldwell, 1975-1976
- Papers relating to international education programs at the University of Maryland, 1965-1966 (2 folders)
- "Home to the East: Notes on the Orient Revisited," by Caldwell, ca. 1961. Typescript
- Miscellaneous papers, 1968-1973
- Correspondence, 1951-1957
- Photographs
- Clippings and miscellany, 1952-1960
- Papers relating to a proposed School of International Studies at American University, Washington, D.C., 1955
- "A Survey of Chinese Literary Criticism," by Caldwell and S. H. She, 1938. Typescript (2 copies)
- Microfiche of O. J. Caldwell's memoirs, Scenes from a Violent Century
- Typescript copy of O. J. Caldwell's memoirs, Scenes from a Violent Century (Box 8.)
- Typescript copy of O. J. Caldwell's manuscript "The Merchants of Light" (Box 9.)
- Typescript copy of O. J. Caldwell's manuscript "Millions of Ronin"
- Typescript copy of O. J. Caldwell's manuscript "How the East- West Center in Hawaii Was Created"
- Post Doctoral Academy of Higher Education Newsletter,March 1979, containing an address by O. J. Caldwell upon his receiving the John E. King Award
- Typescript account by Searle Bates, professor at the University of Nanking, China, in 1937, relating to atrocities committed by the Japanese Army in Nanking in December 1937
- Increments (no correspondence) (Box 10-13)